1. What Is An Algorithm?
A programming algorithm is a computer procedure that is a lot like a recipe (called a procedure) and tells your computer precisely what steps to take to solve a problem or reach a goal. The ingredients are called inputs, while the results are called the outputs.
In programming, algorithm is the set of well defined instruction in sequence to solve a program. An algorithm should always have a clear stopping point.
Qualities of a good algorithm
1.	Inputs and outputs should be defined precisely.
2.	Each step in algorithm should be clear and unambiguous.
3.	Algorithm should be most effective among many different ways to solve a problem.
4.	An algorithm shouldn't have computer code. Instead, the algorithm should be written in such a way that, it can be used in similar programming languages.

Examples Of Algorithms In Programming
Write an algorithm to add two numbers entered by user.
Step 1: Start
Step 2: Declare variables num1, num2 and sum. 
Step 3: Read values num1 and num2. 
Step 4: Add num1 and num2 and assign the result to sum.
        sum←num1+num2 
Step 5: Display sum 
Step 6: Stop
Oil company:

1. Details of distributor who has been alloted max oil in a month:

Step 1:  Start

step 2: initializes all required var columns in db like distributorID, distributorName, oilAlloted/month, oilAllotmentDate, OilSold/month

step 3: collect all the information and store it at required fields.

step 4: from the data collected check which customer has been alloted the maximum oil. Also, check whether they had the max sales 
	previously or not (assuming as they had max sales they were alloted more oil - this may or may not be true always)

step 5: store the required details in descending order with the distributor name and id who has been alloted max. oil . The loop continues until all data is fetched.

step 6: stop

2. Details of distributor who sold max. oil in a month

Step 1:  Start

step 2: initializes all required var columns in db like distributorID, distributorName, oilAlloted/month, oilAllotmentDate, OilSold/month

step 3: collect all the information and store it at required fields.

step 4: from the data collected check which customer has sold maximum oil and how much oil was alloted to him. Also, how much percent of oil has he sold in the month. 
	(We can use this and also compare with previous month details and compare as required like in a particular month sales can be higher than the rest)

step 5: store the required details in descending order with the distributor name and id who has has sold maximum oil . The loop continues until all data is fetched.

step 6: stop

3. Details of customer who sold 50% of oil alloted

Step 1:  Start

step 2: initializes all required var columns in db like distributorID, distributorName, oilAlloted/month, oilAllotmentDate, OilSold/month, 50%OilAlloted

step 3: collect all the information and store it at required fields.

step 4: from the data collected check which customer has sold maximum oil and how much oil was alloted to him.

step 5: Compare the oil alloted and the oil sold during the particular month. Here, we will analyze if the oil sold has crossed 50% mark or not. If it has, using count will increase.
	
step 5: store the required details in descending order with the distributor name and id who has has sold  50% oil. The loop continues until all data is fetched.

step 6: stop

2.  What is Flowchart?
A flowchart is a type of diagram that represents an algorithm, workflow or process, showing the steps as boxes of various kinds, and their order by connecting them with arrows. This diagrammatic representation illustrates a solution model to a given problem. Flowcharts are used in analyzing, designing, documenting or managing a process or program in various fields.
This allows anyone to view the flowchart and logically follow the process from beginning to end.

 /*
 * To change this license header, choose License Headers in Project Properties.
 * To change this template file, choose Tools | Templates
 * and open the template in the editor.
 */
package javaarrayex;

import java.util.Scanner;

/**
 *
 * @author lenovo
 */
public class ArrayHighestValue {
    
               
    public static void main(String[] args) 

    {int n, max;

        Scanner s = new Scanner(System.in);

        System.out.print("Enter number of subjects to be entered in the array:");

        n = s.nextInt();

        int a[] = new int[n];

        System.out.println("Enter number of marks:");

        for(int i = 0; i < n; i++)

        {

            a[i] = s.nextInt();

        }

        max = a[0];

        for(int i = 0; i < n; i++)

        {

            if(max < a[i])

            {

                max = a[i];

            }

        }

        System.out.println("Highest score: " +max);

    }
}


3. What are the basic rules to be followed while creating flowchart?
1. Proper Form is Essential: In drawing a proper flowchart, all necessary requirements should be listed out in logical order.
2. Clarity is Paramount: The flowchart should be clear, neat and easy to follow. There should not be any room for ambiguity in understanding the flowchart.
3. Stick to the Right Direction: The usual direction of the flow of a procedure or system is from left to right or top to bottom.
4. Standard for Flow Lines: Ideally just one flow line should come out from a process symbol.  While only one flow line should enter a decision symbol, around three flow lines (depending on the answer) should leave the decision symbol. Additionally, only one flow line is utilized together with a terminal symbol.
5. Be Concise, not Copious: Write within standard symbols briefly.
6. Logic precedes everything: If you are dealing with a complex flowchart then use connector symbols to minimize the number of flow lines. Ditch the intersection of flow lines to ensure effectiveness and better communication. It is imperative that your flowchart has a logical start and finish.


4. Condition and looping and how they are helpful in applying the logic?                                         
In computer programming, conditional loops or repetitive control structures are a way for computer programs to repeat one or more various steps depending on conditions set either by the programmer initially or real-time by the actual program.
A conditional loop has the potential to become an infinite loop when nothing in the loop's body can affect the outcome of the loop's conditional statement. However, infinite loops can sometimes be used purposely, often with an exit from the loop built into the loop implementation for every computer language, but many share the same basic structure and/or concept. The While loop and the For loop are the two most common types of conditional loops in most programming languages.

1. What is wrapper class in java and what is the use of wrapper class as data type?
Wrapper Class: A Wrapper class is a class whose object wraps or contains a primitive data types. When we create an object to a wrapper class, it contains a field and in this field, we can store a primitive data types. In other words, we can wrap a primitive value into a wrapper class object.
We come across situations where we need to use objects instead of primitive data types. In order to achieve this, Java provides wrapper classes.
All the wrapper classes (Integer, Long, Byte, Double, Float, Short) are subclasses of the abstract class Number.

 

The object of the wrapper class contains or wraps its respective primitive data type. Converting primitive data types into object is called boxing, and this is taken care by the compiler. Therefore, while using a wrapper class you just need to pass the value of the primitive data type to the constructor of the Wrapper class.
And the Wrapper object will be converted back to a primitive data type, and this process is called unboxing. The Number class is part of the java.lang package.

Primitive Data types and their Corresponding Wrapper class
 
Auto boxing: Automatic conversion of primitive types to the object of their corresponding wrapper classes is known as auto boxing. For example – conversion of int to Integer, long to Long, double to Double etc.

Un boxing: It is just the reverse process of auto boxing. Automatically converting an object of a wrapper class to its corresponding primitive type is known as un boxing. For example – conversion of Integer to int, Long to long, Double to double etc.


Need of Wrapper Classes

1.	They convert primitive data types into objects. Objects are needed if we wish to modify the arguments passed into a method (because primitive types are passed by value).
2.	The classes in java.util package handles only objects and hence wrapper classes help in this case also.
3.	Data structures in the Collection framework, such as ArrayList and Vector, store only objects (reference types) and not primitive types.
4.	An object is needed to support synchronization in multithreading.  


2. What is Operator and why it is required in programming?

Operator: Operator in java is a symbol that is used to perform operations. For example: +, -, *, / etc.
There are many types of operators in java which are given below:
o	Unary Operator,
o	Arithmetic Operator,
o	shift Operator,
o	Relational Operator,
o	Bitwise Operator,
o	Logical Operator,
o	Ternary Operator and
o	Assignment Operator.

3. What is Conditional Constructs and why it is required in programming?
Decision making structures have one or more conditions to be evaluated or tested by the program, along with a statement or statements that are to be executed if the condition is determined to be true, and optionally, other statements to be executed if the condition is determined to be false.
 

Sr.No.	Statement & Description
1	if statement
An if statement consists of a boolean expression followed by one or more statements.
2	if...else statement
An if statement can be followed by an optional else statement, which executes when the Boolean expression is false.
3	nested if statement
You can use one if or else if statement inside another if or else if statement(s).
4	switch statement
A switch statement allows a variable to be tested for equality against a list of values.

4. What is difference between if-else and switch case?                                                         
The If statement is used to select among two alternatives. It uses a Boolean expression to decide which alternative should be executed. The switch statement is used to select among multiple alternatives. It uses an int expression to determine which alternative should be executed.      
IF Statement: Checks the value of data is less than or greater than. (in ranges).
Example: Can tell whether an input age is more than 18 and less than 60.

SwitchCase: Checks the value of data that is pre specified. 
Example: Can only generate output if the value matches. When the age is 18 or when the age is 60. No comparison of data based on greater than or smaller than. Compares data based on equality.                   


5. What is looping constructs and why it is required in programming?
     
It tests the condition before executing the loop body. Execute a sequence of statements multiple times and abbreviates the code that manages the loop variable.

Looping constructs in Java are:
•	For statement
•	For-each statement
•	While statement
•	Do while statement

5.	Difference between while, do while and for loop?                                                                         
While Loop: While loop checks for the condition first. so it may not even enter into the loop, if the condition is false.
      Do While Loop: do while loop, execute the statements in the loop first before checks for the                 condition. At least one iteration takes places, even if the condition is false.

    For Loop: for loop is similar to while loop except that
o	Initialization statement, usually the counter variable initialization.
o	A statement that will be executed after each and every iteration in the loop, usually counter variable increment or decrement.


Array to accept 10 numbers and display it in ascending order

package arrayascending_order;
import java.util.Scanner;
public class ArrayAscending_Order {

   
    public static void main(String[] args) {
          {
        int n, temp;
        Scanner s = new Scanner(System.in);
        System.out.print("Enter no. of elements you want in array:");
        n = s.nextInt();
        int a[] = new int[n];
        System.out.println("Enter all the elements:");
        for (int i = 0; i < n; i++) 
        {
            a[i] = s.nextInt();
        }
        for (int i = 0; i < n; i++) 
        {
            for (int j = i + 1; j < n; j++) 
            {
                if (a[i] > a[j]) 
                {
                    temp = a[i];
                    a[i] = a[j];
                    a[j] = temp;
                }
            }
        }
        System.out.println("Ascending Order:");
        for (int i = 0; i < n - 1; i++) 
        {
            System.out.println(a[i] + ",");
        }
        System.out.println(a[n - 1]);
    }
    }
    
}
Output:
Enter no. of elements you want in array: 10
Enter all the elements:
1 21 22 11 34 90 21 15 10 7
Ascending Order:1,7,10,11,15,21,21,22,34,90



Program to accept array of 10 numbers and display its sum and average.

package sum_average;
import java.util.Scanner;
public class Sum_Average {
public static void main(String[] args) {
      {
        int n, sum = 0;
        float average;
        Scanner s = new Scanner(System.in);
        System.out.println("Enter no. of elements you want in array:");
        n = s.nextInt();
        int a[] = new int[n];
        System.out.println("Enter all the elements:");
        for(int i = 0; i < n ; i++)
        {
            a[i] = s.nextInt();
            sum = sum + a[i];
        }
        System.out.println("Sum:"+sum);
        average = (float)sum / n;
        System.out.println("Average:"+average);
    }
} 
}
Output:
Enter no. of elements you want in array:
10
Enter all the elements:
1
23
2
5
10
15
67
80
25
21
Sum: 249
Average: 24.9

Java Program to display matrix of 3 rows and 3 columns.
package matrixex;

import java.util.Scanner;
public class MatrixEx {
    
	Scanner scan;
	int matrix[][];
	int row, column;
 
	void create() {
		
		scan = new Scanner(System.in);
		
		System.out.println("Matrix Creation");
		
		System.out.println("\nEnter the value of 3 rows :");
		row = Integer.parseInt(scan.nextLine());
		
		System.out.println("Enter the value of 3 columns :");
		column = Integer.parseInt(scan.nextLine());
		
		matrix = new int[row][column];
		System.out.println("Enter the data :");
 
		for(int i=0; i<3; i++) {
			
			for(int j=0; j<3; j++) {
				
				matrix[i][j] = scan.nextInt();
			}
		}
        }
	
	void display() {
		
		System.out.println("\nThe Matrix is :");
		
		for(int i=0; i<3; i++) {
			
			for(int j=0; j<3; j++) {
				
				System.out.print("\t" + matrix[i][j]);
			}
			System.out.println();
		}
	}

 


    public static void main(String[] args) 
    {
           MatrixEx mobj = new MatrixEx();
        mobj.create();
		mobj.display();
	}

}
   

Output:
Matrix Creation

Enter the value of 3 rows :
3
Enter the value of 3 columns :
3
Enter the data :
1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9

The Matrix is:
	1	2	3
	4	5	6
	7	8	9


2.  Program to add matrix.


package matrixex;

import java.util.Scanner;
public class MatrixEx {
    
	


    public static void main(String[] args) 
    {
      int m, n, c, d;
      Scanner in = new Scanner(System.in);
 
      System.out.println("Enter the number of rows and columns of matrix");
      m = in.nextInt();
      n  = in.nextInt();
 
      int first[][] = new int[m][n];
      int second[][] = new int[m][n];
      int sum[][] = new int[m][n];
 
      System.out.println("Enter the elements of first matrix");
 
      for (  c = 0 ; c < m ; c++ )
         for ( d = 0 ; d < n ; d++ )
            first[c][d] = in.nextInt();
 
      System.out.println("Enter the elements of second matrix");
 
      for ( c = 0 ; c < m ; c++ )
         for ( d = 0 ; d < n ; d++ )
            second[c][d] = in.nextInt();
 
      for ( c = 0 ; c < m ; c++ )
         for ( d = 0 ; d < n ; d++ )
             sum[c][d] = first[c][d] + second[c][d];  //replace '+' with '-' to subtract matrices
 
      System.out.println("Sum of entered matrices:-");
 
      for ( c = 0 ; c < m ; c++ )
      {
         for ( d = 0 ; d < n ; d++ )
            System.out.print(sum[c][d]+"\t");
 
         System.out.println();
      }
   }
}

Output:
Enter the number of rows and columns of matrix
3
3

Enter the elements of first matrix
 1 2 3
4 5 6
7 8 9
Enter the elements of second matrix
1 2 3
4 5 6
7 8 9
Sum of entered matrices:-
2	4	6	
8	10	12	
14	16	18	


Function Return Type
The return type (or result type) defines and constrains the data type of the value returned from method.
Any method that is not declared void must contain a return statement with a corresponding return value, like this: return return Value; the data type of the return value must match the method's declared return type; you can't return an integer value from a method declared to return a Boolean.
•	Method signature includes this return type.
•	public int show(){ // }

•	We will use methods to do a particular task after completion of task if we want to return something to the calling place these return types will be used.
•	Based on the type of data to be returned will mention it as int, char, float double etc as return type in method signature and return statement should be the last statement of the method body.

A method can also return a reference type. For example, in a program to manipulate Bicycle objects, we might have a method like this:

public Bicycle seeWhoisFastest(Bicycle myBike, Bicycle yourBike,
                              Environment env) {
    Bicycle fastest;
    // code to calculate which bike is 
    // faster, given each bike's gear 
    // and cadence and given the 
    // environment (terrain and wind)
    return fastest;
}

The mechanism used to pass parameters to a procedure (subroutine) or function. 
The most common methods are to pass the value of the actual parameter (call by value), or to pass the address of the memory location where the actual parameter is stored (call by reference). 
Eg.: add(int a, int b)
{
some statements
}

public static void main(String[] args) 
{
  add(12,15); //calling method add
  .............
}
 
3. void is a Java keyword.
Used at method declaration and definition to specify that the method does not return any type, the method returns void.

4. 'args' contains the command-line arguments passed to the Java program upon invocation.String[] args is an array of strings passed into main as parameters.
It's a String because the command line is expressed in text. 
Also, no one knows what the programmer will use. For this reason, with the 'args[]' of type String you can pass N arguments to you program, and convert as you need, because a String can become whatever primitive type in Java.


1.Constructors are special class functions which performs initialization of every object.Java constructor is invoked at the time of object creation. It constructs the values i.e. provides data for the object that is why it is known as constructor. 
  
It is of 2 types: a. Default constructor (no-arg constructor): It has no parameter. provides the default values to the object like 0, null etc. depending on the type. 
			Syntax: ClassName(){}
		  b. Parameterized constructor: A constructor that have parameters is known as parameterized constructor. Parameterized constructor is used to provide different values to the distinct objects. 
		        Syntax: ClassName(parameters){}

2. Constructors are needed to initialize the objects when they are created.It is the means of creating an instance of your class by creating an object in memory and returning a reference to it. 
   Something that should happen in the constructor is that the object is in a proper initial state for the subsequent operations on the object to make sense.

3. Parameterized constructor: A constructor that has parameters is known as parameterized constructor. Parameterized constructor is used to provide different values to the distinct objects. 
		        Syntax: ClassName(parameters){}. Parameters can be like (int a)

4. Rules for Constructor: 
It has two rules: --> Constructor name must be same as its class name
		    --> Constructor must have no explicit return type

5. In Java, constructor of base class with no argument gets automatically called in derived class constructor.But, if we want to call parameterized contructor of base class, then we can call it using super().  
   The point to note is base class comstructor call must be the first line in derived class constructor.
-->super can be used to refer immediate parent class instance variable.
-->super can be used to invoke immediate parent class method.
-->super() can be used to invoke immediate parent class constructor.

6. Consider this eg.:
public class ConstructorEx {

   class Parent // base class or super class
{
  Parent() {
    System.out.println("Base Class Constructor Called ");
  }
}
 
static class Child extends Parent //subclass
{
  Child() {
    System.out.println("Derived Class Constructor Called ");
  }
}
    
    public static void main(String[] args) {
        Child c = new Child();
    }
    
}

Output:
Base Class Constructor Called 
Derived Class Constructor Called 

Now here, when we created the object of child class using new keyword, its constructor is called, ie In a class hierarchy, constructors complete their execution in order of derivation, from superclass to subclass. 
Thus, first the Parent class constructor is called, and after that the child class constructor is called. 
Because the child class inherits from the parent class, both the perent class and child class constructors will be called when a child class object is created.

7.Function overriding, in object oriented programming, is a language feature that allows a subclass or child class to provide a specific implementation of a method that is already provided by one of its superclasses or parent classes.
The benefit of overriding is: ability to define a behavior that's specific to the subclass type, which means a subclass can implement a parent class method based on its requirement.

8. If a class has multiple methods having same name but different in parameters, it is known as Function Overloading. It increases the readability of the program.
There are two ways to overload the method in java:
    -->By changing number of arguments
    -->By changing the data type


9. Inheritance provids a  mechanism that allows a class to inherit the property of another class. When a Class "extends" another class, it inherits all non-private members including fields and methods. 
Inheritance in Java can be best understood in terms of Parent and Child relationship, also known as Super class(Parent) and Sub class(child) in Java language.
Inheritance defines is-a relationship between a Super class and its Sub class. extends and implements keywords are used to describe inheritance in Java.
The derived class inherits all the members and methods that are declared as public or protected. If declared as private it can not be inherited by the derived classes. The private members can be accessed only in its own class.

10. Using the extends keyword. The extends keyword is specified after the class name and before another class name. The class name before extends identifies the child and the class name after extends identifies the parent. 
It's impossible to specify multiple class names after extends because Java doesn't support class-based multiple inheritance.

11. Interface is a 100% abstract class. It contains only constants and method signatures. In other words it is a reference type similar to class. An interface can’t be instantiated. It can be implemented by a class or extended by another interface.
Interfaces provide an alternative to multiple inheritance. Java programming language does not support multiple inheritance. But interfaces provide a good solution. Any class can implement a particular interface and importantly the interfaces are not a part of class hierarchy. 
Interfaces use the "implements" keyword.
A class that implements an interface must provide implementation to all the methods that are declared in the interface.
Interfaces can be used as reference type for the object of an implementing class.
An interface can be extended by another interface.